RG 033, Works Progress Administration for Connecticut
Connecticut State Library
- Series 8. Ethnic Groups Survey, 1942-012
  - 37. Bridgeport office file, 1936-1940 (Box 109)
    - English/Scotch – Bridgeport (edited) – Majorie E. Stuart (Box 111)
    - Germans in Bridgeport – Louise E. Doyle (Box 112)
    - Holland Dutch of Bridgeport (Box 112)
    - People of Connecticut – French – Canadians (Box 112)
    - Germans of Bridgeport (Box 112)
    - Germans of Bridgeport (Box 112)
    - British Americans – Yankees – Bridgeport – Interviews – 1 (Box 112)
    - British Americans – Yankees – Bridgeport – Interviews – 2 (Box 112)
    - Peoples of Connecticut – Hungarian study (Box 113)
    - Hungarians of Bridgeport 1 (Box 113)
    - Hungarians of Bridgeport 2 (Box 113)
    - Interviews – Pearl K. Russo, 1940 (Box 113)
    - Irish of Bridgeport 1 (Box 113)
    - Irish of Bridgeport 2 (Box 113)
    - Irish interviews – May G. Finnell (Box 113)
    - People of Connecticut – job incentives among ethnic groups – Italian interviews Bridgeport (Box 114)
    - Irish interviews – Elizabeth M. Buckingham (Box 114)
    - Italians of Bridgeport 1 (Box 114)
    - Italians of Bridgeport 2 (Box 114)
    - Italians of Bridgeport 3 (Box 114)
    - Jews of Bridgeport (Box 115)
    - Negroes of Bridgeport (Box 115)
    - Peoples of Connecticut – Negro interviews (Box 115)
    - Poles of Bridgeport (Box 115)
    - Poles & Italians (edited) – Vincent Frazzetta – 3 (Box 115)
    - Poles & Italians (edited) – Vincent Frazzetta – 2 (Box 115)
    - Poles & Italians (edited) – Vincent Frazzetta – 1 (Box 115)
    - Russians in Bridgeport (Box 116)
    - Scots of Bridgeport (Box 116)
    - Peoples of Connecticut – job incentives among ethnic groups – Polish interviews of Bridgeport (Box 116)
    - Peoples of Connecticut – interviews with Swedes (Box 116)
    - Swedish interviews – William J. Smallwood (Box 116)
    - Interviews (edited) – Marshall V. Rourke 1 (Box 116)
    - Interviews (edited) – Marshall V. Rourke 2 (Box 116)
    - Interviews – Frank E. Nolan (Box 117)
    - Interviews with students – Bridgeport (Box 117)
    - Biographies – Bridgeport 1 (Box 117)
    - Bridgeport – biographies 2 (Box 117)
    - Bridgeport – biographies (Box 117)
    - Bridgeport community studies (Box 118)
    - Interviews – William Spelman (Box 118)
    - Peoples of Connecticut – ethnic studies 1 (Box 118)
    - Peoples of Connecticut – ethnic studies 2 (Box 118)
    - Newspaper survey 1920 – 1921 – George Fisher 1 (Box 118)
    - Newspaper survey 1920 – 1921 – George Fisher 2 (Box 118)
    - Bridgeport community studies – Block survey (Box 119)
    - Bridgeport block questionnaires – (covering 2 blocks, predominantly Slovak, in Hell’s kitchen tenement area (Box 119)
    - Block survey, Bridgeport 1 (Box 119)
    - Block survey, Bridgeport 2 (Box 119)
  - 38. Hartford office file, 1936-1940 (Box 120)
    - Hartford – Swedes – Johnson (Box 120)
    - Hartford – Danes – Hinrichs (Box 120)
    - Cromwell – racial elements – Cole (Box 120)
    - Torrington – Swiss – Cole (Box 120)
    - Torrington – Czecho-slovaks – Cole (Box 120)
    - Thomaston – racial elements – Cooper (Box 120)
    - North Canaan – racial elements – Cole (Box 120)
    - Waterbury – Lithuanians – Cooper (Box 120)
    - Hartford – Danes – Hinrichs (Box 120)
    - East Hartford – racial elements – Hinrichs (Box 120)
    - New Britain – racial elements – Fink (Box 120)
    - New Hartford – racial elements – Cole (Box 120)
    - New Milford – racial elements – Keating (Box 120)
    - Cromwell – racial elements – Hinrichs (Box 120)
    - Manchester – racial elements – Johnson (Box 120)
    - Wethersfield – racial elements – Hinrichs (Box 120)
    - Winsted – racial elements – Cole (Box 120)
    - Woodbury – Indian lore – Keating (Box 120)
    - 2 – field file – racial geography – (L. J. Robertson & Elsie MacKenzie) (Box 121)
    - 4 - editorial file – Torrington racial elements – (Carrington Phelps) (Box 121)
    - 3 – work file – racial geography – Hartford (Robertson & MacKenzie) (Box 121)
    - 2 – field file – Hartford racial elements (Robertson & MacKenzie) (Box 121)
    - 4 – editorial file – Irish (Robertson) (Box 121)
    - 4 – editorial file – racial elements – Poles in New Britain (McCourt & Fink) (Box 121)
    - Editorial file – French Canadians (McDermott) (Box 121)
    - 2 – field file – Poles in New Britain (MacKenzie) (Box 121)
    - 1 - Reference file – French Canadians in Torrington (Phelps) (Box 121)
    - Hartford – Jews – Rosoff (Box 122)
    - Hartford – Jews – Rosoff (work file) (Box 122)
    - Hartford – racial elements – Ireland (free state) – Smith (Box 122)
    - Hartford – racial geography – Robertson & MacKenzie (Box 122)
    - Berlin – racial elements – Rosoff (Box 122)
    - Middletown – Poles – Scully (Box 122)
    - Middletown – Poles – Scully (Box 122)
    - Hartford – Russians – Stanley (Box 122)
    - Hartford – Russians – Stanley (Box 122)
    - Newspaper excerpts – Katz (Box 123)
    - Dept. stores: schools – domestics etc – Katz (Box 123)
    - Irish group – Curry (Box 123)
    - Polish group – Curry (Box 123)
    - National group names – Polish – Ostapkevich (Box 123)
    - New Britain – city impr. – industry – emigrant – slavery – colonial data – Curry (Box 123)
    - Newspaper excerpts – miscellaneous nationalities – Curry (Box 123)
    - Germans – Curry (Box 123)
    - Swedish group – Curry (Box 123)
    - Yankee – Curry (Box 123)
    - Negro group – Curry (Box 123)
    - New Britain Poles – Fink (Box 123)
    - Foreign press & inter & intra state buses – school data – 169 towns – Katz (Box 123)
    - Ethnic study – state depts. – McKenna (Box 123)
    - “Gilpin players – international night” – McKenna (Box 123)
    - Art, music, drama, etc – McKenna (Box 123)
    - Connecticut charter copy – McKenna (Box 123)
    - Block survey – Jews – McKenna (Box 123)
    - Block survey – French Canadians – McKenna (Box 123)
    - Hartford – Russians – Ostapkevich (Box 124)
    - Ukrainians – Ostapkevich (Box 124)
    - French Canadians – New Britain – provost (Box 124)
    - Stores – ins cos – school data – McKenna (Box 124)
    - Irish interviews – block survey – McKenna (Box 124)
    - Block survey – French Canadians (Box 124)
    - Block survey – interviews with Jews in Hartford – Historical data on Old Goodwin Tavern 1782 (Box 124)
    - Block survey – interview with Poles (Box 124)
    - Block survey – Polish – Governor St – Sheldon St – McKenna (Box 124)
    - “Living in Connecticut” – Bigelow Sanford Co. – McKenna, Robertson (Box 124)
    - Foreign motion pictures – McKenna (Box 124)
    - Barnard material (a new slant on Barnard) – McKenna, Robertson (Box 124)
    - Poles – New Britain (editorial file) – Fink (Box 124)
    - Sons of Italy membership – Ostapkevich (Box 124)
    - Early Swedish history – New Britain – Riley (Box 124)
    - H. P. H. S. Radio sketches – Robertson (Box 124)
    - British American club – Robertson (Box 124)
    - Music – Sugden (Box 124)
    - State depts. – Sugden (Box 124)
    - Previously unfiled (Box 124)
    - Newspaper accounts on labor strikes in Hartford 1 (Box 125)
    - Newspaper accounts on labor strikes in Hartford 2 (Box 125)
    - Newspaper accounts on labor strikes in Hartford 3 (Box 125)
    - Newspaper accounts on labor strikes in Hartford 4 (Box 125)
    - Newspaper accounts on labor strikes in Hartford 5 (Box 125)
    - Ethnic studies in Hartford education – Katz & McKenna (Box 126)
    - State dept of health, physicians (Box 126)
    - Jews of Hartford (Box 126)
    - Previously unfiled (Box 126)
    - Office files & racial groups material (Box 126)
    - Life history survey (Box 126)
    - Labor history of Hartford (Box 126)
    - Newspaper excerpts – Sugden (Box 126)
    - Folklore – folkways (Box 126)
    - Survey of business areas – Katz (Box 126)
    - Federal writers project – (Previously untitled) (Box 126)
    - Hartford Public High School (Box 126)
    - Art, drama & musical groups (Box 126)
    - Business firms & ethnic group of employees (Box 126)
    - Jews – Tonken 1 (Box 126)
    - Jews – Tonken 2 (Box 126)
  - 39. New Britain office file, 1936-1940 (Box 127)
    Edited copy, drafts, interview reports and working papers, often essentially duplicated in central office files.
    - New Britain – industry & labor organizations (Box 127)
    - New Britain – labor leaders interviews (Box 127)
    - New Britain – maladjustment survey (Box 127)
    - New Britain – art survey (Box 127)
    - New Britain – ethnic studies (Box 127)
    - New Britain community studies – early social history (Box 127)
    - New Britain – juvenile delinquency (Box 127)
    - New Britain – study of streets (Box 127)
    - New Britain (Box 127)
    - New Britain, community studies – German group (Box 127)
    - New Britain, community studies – cultural study (Box 127)
    - Italians of New Britain (Box 128)
    - Germans of New Britain (Box 128)
    - Jews of New Britain (Box 128)
    - Germans of New Britain (Box 128)
    - Lithuanians of New Britain (Box 128)
    - Americans of New Britain (Box 128)
    - British Americans of New Britain (Box 128)
    - French Canadians of New Britain (Box 128)
    - Irish of New Britain (Box 128)
    - New Britain Poles – life histories (Box 129)
    - Poles – life histories (Box 129)
    - New Britain – Lithuanians (Box 129)
    - New Britain – Lithuanians (Box 129)
    - Poles of New Britain – economic life 1 (Box 129)
    - Poles of New Britain – economic life 2 (Box 129)
    - Poles – New Britain – general (Box 129)
    - New Britain – Swedes (Box 130)
    - Poles of New Britain – organized life (Box 130)
    - Poles of New Britain – Polish organizations (Box 130)
    - Poles of New Britain – personal histories, interviews 1 (Box 130)
    - Poles of New Britain – personal histories, interviews 2 (Box 130)
    - Poles of New Britain – personal histories, interviews 3 (Box 130)
    - Poles of New Britain – personal histories, interviews 4 (Box 130)
- Series 9. Town and City Histories
  After the completion of the Guide, the Writers' Project staff prepared a number of histories of Connecticut towns and cities. Only two appear to have been published, but the drafts and notes are retained here.
  - 40. "Bridgeport, Connecticut: the story of its economic and social growth", 1939-1941 (Box 131-137)
    Drafts, reference materials, notes and working papers. Several successive drafts of the history are followed by edited copy of research papers on various related subjects, with notes and reference materials.
    There are several identifiable series, arranged by subject, and some unarranged folders.
  - 41. "Clinton, 1663-1937" (Box 138)
    Completed typewritten text, with illustrations, dated May 1, 1937 (281 pages).
  - 42. Materials for a history of Fairfield County, 1940-1941 (Box 139-140)
    A prospectus for a history, with a few draft chapters covering the early period and research materials dealing primarily with "morals" (social customs), recreations, folklore, witchcraft and harbor stories.
  - 43. "Farmington: a New England town", 1939-1941 (Box 141-145)
    An edited draft, in popular style, of a history of Farmington. Also included is an earlier draft (1939) of "A history of Farmington (for the use of schools of Farmington, Conn.)" by L.J. Robertson, Jr. Followed by preliminary copy and related materials
    Some arranged by subject, some by chapter.
  - 44. "Madison, 1645-1938" (Box 146)
    Two copied of a 515-page, typed manuscript history by Louise E. Dew Watrous, with some field notes of other staff workers.
  - 45. Materials for History of Milford, Connecticut, 1639-1939, 1936-1939 (Box 147-153)
    Field notes, drafts, edited copy and other working materials preliminary to the printed history published in 1939 by the Milford Tercentenary Committee, Inc. A copy of the book is in the CSL collection [F104.M7 W7 1939].
    Largely unarranged.
  - 46. Materials for a history of New Britain, 1938-1940 (Box 154-144)
    Draft chapters, field notes, edited copy and other materials pertaining to the history of New Britain. There seems to be no completed manuscript.
  - 47. "The Chronology of Norwalk, 1640-1940", 1938-1940 (Box 156)
    Completed manuscript, by Patten Beard, (four slightly different copies) with small amount of related notes and correspondence. Also typed manuscript of "the story of our town, for Norwalk boys and girls", by Patten Beard.
  - 48. "The making of modern Stamford", 1938-1941 (Box 157-169)
    Completed manuscript (118 typed pages), with earlier drafts, field notes, preliminary reports and drafts, reference materials and correspondence. Included are biographical notes, ethnic studies materials, bibliographies, etc.
    Unarranged except for a few groups by subject.
  - 49. Materials for History of West Haven, Connecticut, 1936-1940 (Box 170-176)
    Field notes, drafts, edited copy and other working materials preliminary to the printed history, published in 1940 by the Town of West Haven.
- Series 10. Histories of City Parks
  Historical and descriptive accounts of the parks and other recreational facilities of several cities were prepared, presumably with the expectation that they could be published by local authorities as tourist information or promotional material.
  - 50. "Recreational facilities of Bridgeport, the Park City", 1938-1941 (Box 177-180)
    Completed, typed manuscript, with related correspondence, work and reference materials, preliminary drafts, etc.
  - 51. Material on the history of Hartford parks, 1938-1940 (Box 181-184)
    Drafts of historical and descriptive material on Hartford parks.
    Two main groups, each alphabetical by name of park, with some general material.
  - 52. Material on the history of New Britain parks, 1938 (Box 185-186)
    Drafts of historical and descriptive material on New Britain parks.
    An empty folder is labeled "A guide to the principal parks of New Britain - File copy", but no manuscript has been found.
  - 53. "New Haven Park Guide", 1936-1938 (Box 187-190)
    Manuscript guide (two versions) to New Haven parks, including historical notes, with manual, administrative correspondence, and drafts, working papers and reference materials.
    See also item 68.
- Series 11. Hartford Flood
  The disastrous storm and flood of March 1936 led W.P.A. officials to turn their efforts wherever possible to assistance, relief and rehabilitation programs. The Writers' Project assigned many of its people to collecting information to document the story of the disaster, of people's reactions to it, and of the rehabilitation work. In Hartford a special effort was made, at the Mayor's request, to prepare a history of the flood, but it appears never to have been completed. A map of Hartford showing flooded areas is in item 105, number 12.
  - 54. Edited copy and draft materials, 1936-1937 (Box 191-194)
    News accounts, interview reports and historical sketches on the experiences of individuals and the performance of various public and private agencies and institutions.
    Two main groups: the first roughly by subject but in numerical folders (incomplete: 8, 10-23, 25-32), the second by name of field worker and there under by subject (unarranged).
- Series 12. Bridgeport Library System
  A project for the preparation of a history of the Bridgeport public library system was begun in 1938. An 84 page draft entitled "The Bridgeport library system" was completed in 1941 but never published.
  - 55. Final draft and working materials, 1938-1941 (Box 195)
    Two copies of the final text, a corrected copy of the preceding draft, material on the librarian's comments, and working materials and preliminary drafts.
- Series 13. History of Norwalk Schools
  A substantial amount of work was done by Miss Patten Beard for a publication on this subject, to be entitled "The development of a New England school system". Evidently no manuscript was completed.
  - 56. Field copy and administrative correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 196-197)
- Series 14. History of Hartford Public High School
  - 57. Field notes, copy and drafts of reports and radio scripts, 1938 (Box 198)
- Series 15. History of Labor in Connecticut
  - 58. Field notes, copy and drafts of reports, 1938-1939 (Box 199-200)
    Initiated as part of the Ethnic Groups Survey.
    Materials on the history of labor in the state and in individual cities, with biographies of leaders, newspaper excerpts, etc.
- Series 16. "Patriotic Pamphlets"
  W.P.A. agreed with the State Department of Education to prepare a series of pamphlets on various aspects of Connecticut history to be used in the schools. Substantial progress was made on some of them, up to the point of dummies and edited copy, but evidently nothing was published except
  Koenig, Immigrant Settlements in Connecticut, 1938
  .
  - 59. Drafts, notes and research materials, 1938-1942 (Box 201-204)
    Roughly grouped by topic: a comparison of Connecticut life in 1841 and 1941, "The clockmakers of Connecticut", "Defenders of democracy (biographical sketches), "Settlement of western lands of Connecticut", "shipping and shipbuilding on the Connecticut River" (completed manuscript), and "the Farmington Canal" (completed manuscript). The last item was printed but withheld from distribution; a copy is in the file, titled
    Boats Across New England Hills
- Series 17. Studies of New England Life
  The New England Regional Office planned a study in 1938 to consist of sketches of individual New Englanders in varying occupations and of different ethnic origins. The text of the proposed book was intended to be presented largely in the words of the subjects, describing their own lives, but with accompanying historical and folklore material. Nothing appears to have been published, but the project remained active for several years in Connecticut and a good deal of preparatory material was collected. The plan underwent several modifications and was known at different times as "Living lore in New England", "Living in New England", "Working in New England", "Men at Work" and "Hands that built New England".
  - 60. Field notes, drafts, working papers and correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 205-209)
    Subjects include, e.g., Portuguese, tobacco, Remington arms, knife makers, brass industry, clockmakers, Henry Barnard (19th century educator), "May breakfast" (later designed for the "America eats" project.
    Largely unarranged although in folders labeled by subject with a numbered series at the beginning.
- Series 18. Folklore and Folkways
  - 61. Outline and working files, 1936-1937 (Box 210-211)
    Interview reports, notes and drafts.
    Unarranged but labeled by subject.
- Series 19. New Haven Tercentenary
  - 62. Pamphlets and related materials, 1938-1939 (Box 212-214)
    Final texts of pamphlet copy on historical subjects by Iveagh H. Lewis and William H. Garrigus, printed posters/broadsides, and related notes, drafts and other preparatory materials for these and for a proposed pageant or radio program on New Haven history.
- Series 20. Survey of City Governments
  This nationwide project, later known as the Municipal Government Subproject, was sponsored by the United States Conference of Mayors to collect a reference file of source materials and reports on the structure, laws, codes, and administration of the larger cities.
  - Instructions, reports, reference materials and field notes, 1936 (Box 215)
    Grouped by city.
- Series 21. W.P.A. Histories
  - 64. Summary accounts of the Connecticut W.P.A. program, 1935-1937 (Box 216-217)
    Brief histories, by town, of the W.P.A. accomplishments in each town as of approximately January 1937. Also field notes on this subject, followed by accounts of individual projects. Miscellaneous material at the beginning includes a chronology of the Connecticut W.P.A. from June 8, 1935 to May 20, 1936.
- Series 22. Hurricane
  At the time of the great hurricane and flood of September 1938, all Connecticut W.P.A. writers were asked to record their personal experiences and impressions and to collect other human interest and news stories. (A separate undertaking resulted in the publication of a pamphlet
  A photographic history of the hurricane and flood which devastated Connecticut on September 21, 1938
  . A copy is in Box 333.
  - 65. Field notes and copy, 1938 September-October (Box 218)
- Series 23. United States Travel Atlas
  - 66. Final copy and work files, 1941 (Box 218)
    Material on Connecticut for a proposed country-wide project.
- Series 24. Vacation Guide
  - 67. Work files, 1939 (Box 219)
    Preliminary material for a pamphlet guide to be called "Your vacation in Connecticut". Published in 1940 as
    Connecticut: American Recreation Series, by Bacon and Wieck, Inc.
    (copy in first folder).
- Series 25. New Haven Summer Recreation Guide
  - 68. Drafts and related papers, 1937-1941 (Box 219)
    Drafts, copy, notes, correspondence and mimeographed published copies (1939 and 1941) of "A guide to summer recreation", published by the New Haven Council of Social Agencies.
- Series 26. Coast Guard Academy History
  - 69. Text and related notes, undated (Box 219)
    An incomplete text (26 pages) and some notes for a proposed pamphlet history of the Academy at New London.
    Other records including manuscripts, notes and photographs, were removed on August 18, 1942 by Lucy R. Holabird of W.P.A. Headquarters, New Haven.
- Series 27. Miscellaneous Writers' Project Material
  - 70. State editorial copy - miscellaneous, 1936-1938 (Box 220)
    Includes related administrative correspondence.
    - Guide makers and making (Box 220)
    - America eats (Box 220)
    - Aviafauna (Box 220)
    - Connecticut arms (Box 220)
    - Folkways (Box 220)
    - Health and social work (Box 220)
    - Hurricane (Box 220)
    - Liquor laws (Box 220)
    - Washington trip across Connecticut (Box 220)
    - Makers of the Constitution (Box 220)
    - Moodus noises (see item 105, number 22) (Box 220)
    - New Britain social survey - girls (Box 220)
    - Speech essay (Box 220)
    - Trade jargon (Box 220)
    - US1 guide book (Box 220)
    - Skiing almanac (Box 220)
  - 71. Pageants and radio programs, 1936-1940 (Box 221-222)
    Scripts, texts and related materials.
  - 72. Miscellaneous drafts, notes, etc., 1936-1941
    - "Speech essay" copy on Connecticut dialects (Box 223)
    - Louise E. Dew Watrous papers (Box 223)
    - Moodus industry notes (Box 223)
    - "I slept with a gorilla" (Box 223)
    - "What my Writers' Project job means to me" (Box 223)
    - Index lists, 3 folders (Box 224)
    - Bibliographies of Connecticut history, 3 folders (Box 224)
    - New Britain maladjustment survey papers ("Juvenile delinquent study" probably a part of the Ethnic Groups Survey work) (Box 224)
    - Work files of individual workers, containing materials on various projects, 4 folders (Box 224)
    - "Arborial bearings" containing two watercolor renderings of the State seal (Box 224)
    - Stratford town history (Box 224)
    - Lists of Writers' Project publications, 2 display cards (Box 224)
- Series 28. Architectural Survey, Census of Old Buildings
  This project began as a part of the task of compiling material for the guidebook
  Connecticut, A Guide to its Roads, Lore, and People
  . Mr. Elmer D. Keith, who had edited the important Colonial Dames books on historic Connecticut houses, was responsible for "the architectural end." Using the Colonial Dames books, the Heermance (State Planning Board) guide, and actual one-day visits to each town by members of his small staff, he compiled form reports on nearly 5,000 buildings, illustrated with photographs, and also prepared descriptions of nearly all towns, with reference to their historic buildings.
  - 73. Building survey reports, 1934-1937; 1942-013